<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="loc">
  <title>location argument type</title>
  <simplesect role="description" id="gen-000"><title>Description</title>
	  <para>One of: 
	    <literal>after</literal>, 
	    <literal>before</literal>, 
	    <literal>into</literal>,
	    <literal>append</literal>,
	    <literal>prepend</literal>,
	    <literal>replace</literal>.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This argument is required by all commands that insert
	    nodes to a document in some way to a destination described
	    by an XPath expression. The meaning of the values listed
	    above is supposed be obvious in most cases, however the
	    exact semantics for location argument values depends on
	    types of both the source node and the target node.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <literal>after/before</literal> place the node right
	    after/before the destination node, except for when the
	    destination node is a document node or one of the source
	    nodes is an attribute: If the destination node is a
	    document node, the source node is attached to the
	    end/beginning of the document (remember: there is no
	    "after/before a document").  If both the source and
	    destination nodes are attributes, then the source node is
	    simply attached to the element containing the destination
	    node (remember: there is no order on attribute nodes). If
	    the destination node is an attribute but the source node
	    is of a different type, then the textual content of the
	    source node is appended to the value of the destination
	    attribute (i.e. in this case after/before act just as
	    append/prepend).
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <literal>append/prepend</literal> appends/prepends the
	    source node to the destination node. If the destination
	    node can contain other nodes (i.e. it is an element or a
	    document node) then the entire source node is attached to
	    it. In case of other destination node types, the textual
	    content of the source node is appended/prepended to the
	    content of the destination node.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <literal>into</literal> can also be used to place
	    the source node to the end of an element (in the same way
	    as <literal>append</literal>), to attach an attribute
	    to an element, or, if the destination node is a text node,
	    cdata section, processing-instruction, attribute or comment,
	    to replace its textual content with the textual content of 
	    the source node.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <literal>replace</literal> replaces the entire destination
	    node with the source node except for the case when the
	    destination node is an attribute and the source node is
	    not. In such a case only the value of the destination
	    attribute is replaced with the textual content of the
	    source node. Note also that document node can never be
	    replaced.
	  </para>
	</simplesect>
  <simplesect id="gen-001">
    <title>Sections</title>
    <para><ulink url="s_Argtypes.html">Argument Types</ulink>, <ulink url="s_Manipulation.html">Tree modification</ulink></para>
  </simplesect>
</section>
